Mariano Riva Palacio Collection:
University of Texas at Austin
Mariano Riva Palacio Collection
1716-1880 (bulk 1835-1875)
Riva Palacio, Mariano, 1803-1880.
7 linear feet
29925371
Benson Latin American Collection, The University of Texas at Austin
Correspondence and official documents of Mariano Riva Palacio, thrice governor of the State of Mexico, pertaining to the governance of Mexico at federal, state, and local levels during the 19th century. This page describes Part 6 of the 17 total parts in the Mariano Riva Palacio Collection guide.
Biographical Sketch
Political leader. Born 1803 and died 1880 in Mexico City. Educated as lawyer. Offices held: Primer Regidor del Ayuntamiento de México (1829), deputy to the Congreso de la Unión (first elected 1833), Minister of Justice, Minister of Hacienda (June-Aug. 1848), thrice Governor of the State of Mexico (1849, 1857, 1871), Director del Nacional Monte de Piedad. Imprisoned 1852-1854 during final presidency of Antonio López de Santa Anna. Named Emperor Maximilan's defender in May 1867. Worked to develop Mexico's law enforcement system, roads, railways, and industry.
For a complete chronology of Mariano Riva Palacio, see Part 1: Introduction to this guide.
Scope and Contents Note
The collections pertains to the governance of Mexico at federal, state, and local levels, to management of various institutions and haciendas, to social and economic conditions in Mexico, and to the activities of Mariano Riva Palacio and many other well-known figures of 19th century Mexico, plus documents relating to the settlement of the estate of Vicente Guerrero. Other names prominent in the collection are Juan Álvarez, Mariano Arista, Ignacio Comonfort, Atilano Sánchez Garayo, and Antonio López de Santa Anna.
This page presents Part 6: January-June 1850 of the collection guide. To access other parts of the guide see Related Material.
Arrangement
Arrangement is primarily chronological, with items numbered in accordance with the published guide:
Dabbs, Jack Autrey. The Mariano Riva Palacio Archives: A Guide (University of Texas. Library. Independent Mexico in documents: Independence, Empire, and Republic; Vol. 2, pt. 1-3) Mexico: Editorial Jus, 1955.
Related Material
The item level description of this guide follows the published calendar The Mariano Riva Palacio Archives: A Guide by Jack Autrey Dabbs (three volumes, with index). Due to the size of the electronic files, the online version of this guide is divided into 17 parts as follows:
Part 1: 1716-1836
Part 2: 1837-1844
Part 3: 1845-1846
Part 4: 1847-1848
Part 5: 1849
Part 6: January-June 1850
Part 7: July-December 1850
Part 8: 1851-1854
Part 9: 1855-1856
Part 10: January-June 1857
Part 11: July-December 1857
Part 12: 1858-1867
Part 13: 1868-1869
Part 14: 1870
Part 15: January-June 1871
Part 16: July-December 1871
Part 17: 1872-1880
Calendar of Items
- Enero-Junio 1850
  - 3668 García, Juan M. Chalco, January 1, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for appointment as prefect.
  - 3669 Diez de Sollano, José María. Mexico, January 1, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Recommendation made by Flores; trip to Puebla and Cholula; plan for opening church. Includes draft of answer, January 7: Receipt of disertación on “La pureza de la Sma. Virgen”; meeting with Domínguez and Cervantes at Cuautla; agreement with Álvarez for removal of remains of Guerrero; tomb of Rodríguez; Colegio de San Gregorio.
  - 3670 Durán, José Ignacio. Mexico, January 1, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Olaguíbel's claim on state-owned books; need for Buffon's works in Department of Biology. Includes draft of answer, January 7: Need for books in Colegio de Toluca; program for obtaining new books at San Gregorio.
  - 3671 Terreros, Manuel. Mexico, January 1, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for use of influence in obtaining appointment to Tribunal Superior de Justicia for Lic. Manuel Sánchez Hidalgo, Juez de Letras de Tulancingo. Embossed design: Crown with letters “Patent under BATH.”
  - 3672 Jimeno, Manuel. Mexico, January 2, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Captain Felipe Bega, applicant for post in Seguridad pública.
  - 3673 Riva Palacio, Mariano. [Borrador de carta a José de Barrientos.] Morelos, January 2, 1850., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Interview with P. Castillo and effort to enlist his support; Castillo's trip to Mexico to confer with prelates; settlement of differences with padre cura; Lucas de Urrutia.
  - 3674 Segura, Sebastián. Hacienda de la Asunción, January 3, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Effort to meet Governor at Toluca; protest against appointment of Ildefonso Flores as Ensayador de Pachuca during writer's absence in Congress; recommendation for Francisco María Garnica; shipment of silver; recommendation of Atilano Sánchez; Minería No. 1; Calle de San Andrés. Includes draft of answer, January 7: Garnica's lack of qualifications.
  - 3675 González de la Vega, José M. Mexico, January 3, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for Andrés Arcipreste, Administrador de Tenancingo, to be transferred to Administrador de contribuciones de Cuautitlán; inheritance suit at Cuautitlán. Has draft of answer, January 7: Appointment of Villamil to Cuautitlán.
  - 3676 Larreátegui, José Mariano. Mineral de Guadalupe, January 3, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Inspection of mine at Hacienda de Tonales; letter to Juan Álvarez for boundary settlement; suit brought before Diputación de Minas de Taxco and Diputación de Temascaltepec; complications caused by negotiations with Esteban Vicente León; request for finding in favor of Taxco; discussion of facts with Juan F. Durán; purchase of mine from Dr. Barrientos.
  - 3677 Sierra y Rosso, Ignacio. Dirección general de Aduanas Marítimas Fronterizas y Rentas no Estancadas, Mexico, January 4, 1850. ALS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Request for favorable consideration in an instancia involving a sicl man and an ignorant woman.
  - 3678 Cruz, Agustín. Toluca, January 4, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Examination of Ayuntamiento reports; effort to arrange affairs in Almoloya district to avoid conflict with Padre Villaseñor; establishment of a Liceo (“logia disimulada”) with Ramírez as president; meeting at the Instituto del Estado; Vicente; Carlos; Pedro; Blas; Escudero.
  - 3679 P[érez] Palacios, Luis. Hacienda de Apanq[]co (?), January 4, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Receipt of call for special session of Congress; death of sister; excuse for not attending meetings; public affairs in Yautepec.
  - 3680 Sánchez Solís, Felipe. Toluca, January 4, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Receipt of funds for purchase of mattresses, pillows, and sheets for new students; Haro's preoccupation with Peña and Echeverría; loan on houses in Mexico; Martínez de Castro; Dr. Magos; tuition owed by students sponsored by municipalidades; Chair of Botany; payments by Méndez and Sosa; debts of González and Mañón (?).
  - 3681 Calderón, Lorenzo. Sultepec, January 4, 1850. LS., 4 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Governor's visit to Cuernavaca; offer to meet the party at Temascaltepec; need for reforms; invitation to Convento de N. P. S. Diego; travel to Zacualpam; orderliness of fair at Zacualpam; effect of revolutions on the district; organization of Fuerzas rurales; illness of Alas; election of Diputación de minería; data on sorteo del Alumno; elections to Ayuntamiento de Zacualpam; Tenancingo; Tecualoya; Chalma; Tetecala; rumors from Lagos of concentration of men to proclaim Bustamante or Santa Anna dictator near Silao; letter from León on strength of the monarchists; Arista; need for stronger military forces.
  - 3682 León, Esteban V. Tem[ascaltepe]c, January 5, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Letters left with Rom[ul]o Díaz in Toluca; need for pay for soldiers; seditious mail sent from Mexico; need for weapons.
  - 3683 Cumplido, Ignacio. Mexico, January 5, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Meeting with Barajas at house of Otero; Otero's eye infection; settlement of account; biographical album for Rodríguez; need for use of letters of condolence; Sabino Flores; gift of calendar.
  - 3684 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, January 5, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Receipt of recommendations from Prefecto Agustín Cruz.
  - 3685 _____. Mexico, January 5, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Sub-lieutenant Joaquín Téllez placed in charge of artillery being sent to Cuernavaca.
  - 3686 [ESTADO DE GUERRERO.] Al Congreso Gral. Iguala, January 6, 1850. Unsigned., 1 l. 21 × 29 cm.
    List of members proposed for Legislature: Senadores Propietarios: General José María Tornel and Juan de Dios Cañedo; suplentes: General Nicolás Bravo and Lic. José María Cuevas. Deputies: Propietarios, Bishop Manuel Pardío, Pedro Fernández del Castillo, Ignacio Durán, Miguel Arrioja, and Colonel Antonio García y García; Suplentes: Lic. José María Jiménez, Joaquín González de la Vega, Santos Degollado, Anastacio Zerecero, and José María Espino. Al Congreso del Estado: Propietarios, General Nicolás Bravo, Colonel Diego Álvarez, Juan José Callejas, José María Añorve de Salas, Félix María Leyva, Ignacio Castañón, Miguel Ibarra, Ignacio Cid del Prado, Eugenio Vargas, Tomás Gómez, and José María Cervantes; Suplentes, Manuel Gómez Daza, Br. Antonio Cano, Carlos Bravo, Miguel Quiñones, José Sierra, Ignacio Zamora, Mariano Herrera, Agustín Patiño, Juan B. Solís, Isidro Román, and Luis Guillemano.
  - 3687 García, Fernando. Cuernavaca, January 6, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Gift of bananas from Costa Rica via Diego Villaseñor.
  - 3688 Romero, José María. Toluca, January, 7, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Delay in opening special session reported by Alejandro Villaseñor; Aguirre; Barquera at the Tribunal; departure of Lieutenant Governor for Mexico, seeking cure for daughter with epilepsy.
  - 3689 Haro, Benito. Iturbide, January 7, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Copy of letter sent to José Joaquín de Herrera on impasse in Legislature; proposal for new constitution; temporary agreement between Bravo and Álvarez; departure for Mexico.
  - 3690 Couto, B[ernardo]. Mexico, January 8, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 28 cm.
    Settlement of debt; death of Peña [y Peña]; eulogy of Peña.
  - 3691 Álvarez, Juan. Ciudad de Iturbide, January 8, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Transmittal of list of Senators and Deputies and members of a constituent congress for the state; meeting at San Gabriel; discovery of rich mine by Luis G. Medero in Cerro de Xochimanca and the Hacienda de San Gaspar; request for protection during working of the mine from Mateo de la Tijera.
  - 3692 Medero, Dto. (?) Amado. Iguala, January 8, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for protection for new mines of Luis G. Medero his uncle at Hacienda de Xochimanca against Mateo de la Tijera; likelihood of finding an excellent salitre soon; return to Guerrero with Álvarez; Padre Catalán.
  - 3693 Peña, J. de la. Morelos, January 8, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Correction of error made by recommending resignation of Manuel Pizarro instead of request for leave.
  - 3694 Lacunza [José María]. Mexico, January 8, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Shortage of verdaderos republicanos in Congress; request that Pedro Escudero be urged to attend.
  - 3695 Zedillo, Salvador. Mexico, January 9, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Preparations for attending meeting of Congress; inability of Aguirre to attend because of illness; Monasterio; recaudador de Tlalpan; return of Governor to Toluca via Coyoacán.
  - 3696 Ansoátegui, P. de. Mexico, January 9, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 20 × 25 cm.
    Request for use of influence to improve Mexican industry.
  - 3697 Flores, Sabino. Mexico, January 9, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Preparation for opening of school; Fonseca; proposal for course in law, taught by Galicia.
  - 3698 Gorospe, Manuel M. Mexico, January 9, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Javier Lagardo (?) for place in the guardia de policía.
  - 3699 Téllez, Joaquín. Cuernavaca, January 9, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Transmittal of papers from private archive of Rodríguez Puebla on request of Barajas; correspondence with Arista over his appointment to Cuernavaca; meeting at San Gabriel.
  - 3700 Aparicio, José María. Cuernavaca, January 9, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for excuse from attending special session because of illness.
  - 3701 Catalán, Prudencio. Tixtla de Guerrero, January 9, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Meeting with Álvarez at San Gabriel; debt paid by Goribar; Dolores; request for influence to have the capital placed in Tixtla; Feliciana.
  - 3702 Mata, José Manuel de. San Felipe del Obrage, January 9, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Manuel Fernández.
  - 3703 Castañares, José Joaquín. Mexico, January 9, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Account of illness and poverty; health of Lola, Pepe, and Loreto.
  - 3704 León, Esteban V. Tem[ascaltepe]c, January 9, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Report on actions of Alcalde and of Francisco Calderón in maintaing order in Ayuntamiento elections in Zacualpan; need for pay for troops; influence of Lic. Alas; calmness in District of Cuernavaca.
  - 3705 Romero, José María. Toluca, January 10, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Receipt of copies of the law on the National Debt; arrangements for printing in El Porvenir; arrangements with Iturbe for road-building; Juan María Flores; Aguirre, Villaseñor.
  - 3706 Sánchez Munibe, Joaquín. Fielato de Yautepec, Yautepec, January 10, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Transmittal of Estado general and report on debts of Municipal funds.
  - 3707 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Texcoco, January 10, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for pay for troops and improvement of the archives; size of the archives; tax sent to Cruz.
  - 3708 Calderón, Lorenzo. Sultepec, January 11, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Arrival of León from Temascaltepec; meeting of hacendados for organization of fuerza rural; meeting in Toluca; Alas.
  - 3709 León, Esteban V. Sultepec, January 11, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Interview with Calderón; travel from Tem[ascaltepe]c.
  - 3710 Icaza, Juan Rafael de. Mexico, January 11, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for excuse from attending special session on account of illness; Sánchez.
  - 3711 Riva Palacio, Mariano. [Borrador de carta a Bernardo Couto, y otra a Doña Cristina Soto.] Toluca, January 11, 1850., 2 l. 21 × 31 cm.
    Death of Peña y Peña; trip through District of Cuernavaca; special session, settlement of account with Doña Cristina.
  - 3712 Solórzano, Mariano. Tenancingo, January 11, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Meeting at San Gabriel; illness; gift of bananas from Costa Rica.
  - 3713 Márquez, Antonio. Jonacatepec, January 12, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for special permission for son of Antonio Sarco to enter the city school, payments chargeable through the Administración de rentas; request for the Governor to sponsor the boy in school.
  - 3714 Barrio, J. N. del. Mexico, January 12, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Manuel Sánchez Hidalgo for the Tribunal Superior; service with Juzgado de Tulancingo; return to Tesuisco (Temisco?).
  - 3715 Iturbe, Francisco. Mexico, January 12, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Governor's trip through Tierra Caliente; plan for building roads from the capital to the interior, to Tepeji del Río, and to Arroyozarco; payment by toll collection; toll on Cuautitlán road.
  - 3716 Álvarez, Juan. Iguala, January 12, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Transmittal of list of Senators, deputies, and members of the Legislatura Constituyente del Estado (missing); agreement on contract for road to Acapulco submitted to General Bravo; Larreátegui; cattle sent to La Providencia.
  - 3717 Carbajal, F. Mexico, January 12, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for extension of leave from duties as editor; indefiniteness of the new Ayuntamiento; alcabala project before Congress; settlement of accounts; brother's position in collection of tolls; Lic. Zenande recommended as substitute.
  - 3718 [Guerrero de Riva Palacio,] Dolores. Mexico, January 12, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Death of Marcelina Paeli(?); Comadre Mejía; [E]chevarría.
  - 3719 Godoy, José María. Mexico, January 12, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Removal of Covarrubias by Governor of Querétaro and replacement by Senator Reyes; danger of heavy financial loss as result of a change of government; need for attendance by Escudero; Yáñez' trip to Veracruz; danger of losing control in Congress; Conservatives and Santanistas; new members from State of Guerrero; problem of Jesuits; Coyoacán; Doloritas; efforts of “B.” to alienate his mines; La Luz; San José; polcos.
  - 3720 [Sin firma.] Tiro de Jesús Nazareno, January 13, 1850. Incomplete., 1 l. 21 × 31 cm.
    Addressed to Mi estimado padrino; efforts to remove water from mines; lawsuits concerning mines; Nanchititla; Lucas; Manuel; letter transmitted by José de Paz; money needed for payroll; check on Valle de Temascaltepec for Rufino; houses in Tejupilco.
  - 3721 Vela, Miguel. Temamatla, January 13, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Petition of Francisco de Sales for change in land ownership at Cuigingo; agreement of Velázquez; Pepe Colín.
  - 3722 Quijano, Benito. Mexico, January 13, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Appointment of Colonel Martínez as fiscal in the trial of Lieutenant Colonel Villegas; contribution for Rancho de San José Cuautla; hardship caused by war; request for easier terms of payment.
  - 3723 Padilla, Anacleto. Temamatla, January 14, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Election as Alcalde principal; request for prompt end to suit over ownership of Cuigingo; mi hermano Pepe.
  - 3724 Pacheco, Juan J. Hacienda de Oacalco, January 14, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for favorable action on request of Jesús Navarro for permission to cultivate cane fields in area under litigation with Tijera.
  - 3725 Haro y Tamariz, A. de. Mexico, January 14, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Illness of brother Joaquín; visit with Martínez del Río; request for lifting of restrictions on games; investments of businessmen in games in Texcoco; substitution of a tax on games suggested, proceeds to go to the Instituto literario.
  - 3726 Acevedo, Pedro L. Sultepec, January 14, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Passport to Mineral de Temascaltepec; services as doctor with Esteban V. León by order of Juan Álvarez; imprisonment by Judge Cayetano Gómez over incident at a dance; support of Lorenzo Calderón cited.
  - 3727 Audelo (Andelo?), José Mariano. Tenancingo, January 14, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Account of his illness and poverty; offer to sell his horse for living expenses; aid by Don Andrés.
  - 3728 Noriega, A. Tlalnep[]a, January 14, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Visit to Cuautitlán; incompetence of the Subprefecto; inadequacy of the Guardia nacional; agreement with Colonel José María Zúñiga for removal of Captain Román González and disbanding of the Guardia nacional; care of the guns; weapons at Zumpango; Joaquín.
  - 3729 PREFECTURA DE TULANCINGO. [Resolución al Subprefecto de Pachuca.] Mineral del Monte, January 15, 1850. Copy., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Move to separate Mineral del Monte from Mineral de Pachuca and Mineral del Chico; election of officials; Real del Monte; division of the archives.
  - 3730 Flores Pensado, Ignacio. Mexico, January 15, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Preparation for opening of school; Durán; settlement of Buffon dispute; Galicia's course in law; Flores; maneuvering among teachers for favorite courses; Lozano; Ángel; Padre Torres; Sollano; courses in arts and philosophy; Obispo de Tenagra; courses in Theology, Greek, Latin, Literature, and English; fear that Colegio de San Gregorio may turn into a seminary; tomb of Rodríguez [Puebla]; Zosaya.
  - 3731 Flores, Sabino. Mexico, January 15, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 20 × 26 cm.
    Fear of José María Rojas of being shot by Ignacio Oliveros; visit to Hacienda de la Asunción; suspicions of Oliveros in Amecameca; request for protection.
  - 3732 Segura, Sebastián. Mexico, January 15, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Protest against appointment of Ildefonso Flores as Ensayador de Pachuca during his absence to attend Congress; recommendation for interim appointment of Francisco María Garnica.
  - 3733 MINISTERIO DE GUERRA Y MARINA. [Permiso a los Sres. Empresarios García, Despous, y Kern para que armen a sus dependientes.] Mexico, January 16, 1850. Copy, originally signed: Arista., 1 l. 21 × 32 cm.
    Copy of letter to Ministro de Relaciones; increase in traffic from Mexico to Veracruz; insecurity of roads; notice to Puebla.
  - 3734 Noriega, A. Tlalnepantla, January 16, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Travel to Santa Fe to insure public order; replacement of road guards by men from Tlalpam; Lic. Villar; public order in Cuautitlán and Zumpango; effort to open school of San Ángel; Marianita; Joaquín; Juan Martínez; Julián.
  - 3735 Buchan, Juan H. [Carta a Escandón.] Dirección de la Compañía de Minas y del Real del Monte, January 17, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 31 cm.
    Favorable attitude of Governor toward separation of Real del Monte from Pachuca; order of Prefecto de Tulancingo separating jurisdiction; opposition of Pachuca; Mineral del Chico; legal precedents.
  - 3736 Lombardo, Francisco M. Mexico, January 17, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 22 × 27 cm.
    Petition of the Vicario de Cuajimal concerning frequent thefts and robberies; recommendation for Vicario José María Luna.
  - 3737 Atristain, Miguel. Mexico, January 17, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Luis Ramírez, Subprefecto de Actopan; explanation of elections for Ayuntamiento in Mixquiah[]a.
  - 3738 _____. Mexico, January 17, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for favorable action on petition of town of Ozumbilla; details given to Escudero; advice of the Marqués de Salinas.
  - 3739 Haro y Tamariz, A. de. Mexico, January 17, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Return from Valle de San Martín; letter from Sánchez Solís; funds for Instituto Literario from bequests; advice of Ramón de la Cueva; Hacienda de Acucuilco; brother Joaquín; medical opinion of brother.
  - 3740 Sánchez Solís, Felipe. Mexico, January 17, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Interview with Haro; preparations for opening school.
  - 3741 Barajas, Ceferino. Mexico, January 17, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Assignment of teachers and courses; Galicia; I. Flores; Sabino Flores; Fonseca.
  - 3742 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Mexico, January 17, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Purchase of horses and weapons; Blancs; request for the law on games; illness of son Pancho; guards from Río Frío; Rebollar.
  - 3743 Flores, Sabino. Mexico, January 18, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 20 × 25 cm.
    Assignment of Law course to Galicia and grammar to Ignacio Flores; Fonseca; assignment of Philosophy course; Padre Torres; El Siglo; Cumplido.
  - 3744 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Mexico, January 18, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Receipt of instructions on treatment of games at Texcoco; son Ignacio; purchase of horses and sabers; Blancs.
  - 3745 Gutmany, S. de. Mexico, January 18, 1850. ALS. Signed “por enfermedad de Manuel Escandón.”, 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Transmittal of petition from Prefectura de Tulancingo, sent by Director de la Compañía de Minas del Real del Monte.
  - 3746 Álvarez, Juan. Ciudad de Iturbide, January 19, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm Printed letterhead.
    Correspondence with José María Lacunza and Nicolás Bravo over road to Acapulco; Río de Amacuzac.
  - 3747 _____. Iguala, January 19, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.